how to choose the best garbage collector
for your use case before we do that
let's try to understand some of the
garbage collection concepts we will talk
about trade-offs their generational GC
and two algorithms called mark and copy
and mark and sweep so let's start with
trade-offs when we talk about garbage
collection we generally have to consider
three things the first thing is the
memory this is the amount of memory that
is assigned to the program this is also
called as the heap the second thing that
we need to understand is the true put
throughput is how much amount of time
that a code is run compared to how much
amount of time your garbage collection
is run so for example if the throughput
is 99% that means that 99% of the time
your code was running and 1% of the time
that garbage collection was running so
of course ideally you would want as much
higher throughput as possible and the
third aspect that we need to understand
is the latency latency is whenever
garbage collection runs how much amount
of time our program stops for the
garbage collection to run properly these
are generally measured in milliseconds
but they can go up to a few seconds
depending on the size of the memory and
the garbage collection algorithm that
issues ok of course ideally we would
want the latency to be as low as
possible or as predictable as possible
the second concept that we need to learn
is called generational hypothesis this
hypothesis says that most objects die
young
so whenever you use any object or
variable whenever you create object or
variable within a function or within a
for loop and that does not escape the
for loop or function so it is limited
only to that scope then of course as
soon as the core comes out of the for
loop or comes out of the function that
object is eligible for garbage
collection so this hypothesis says that
most of our variables are of this kind
they die young and that is why many of
the garbage collection algorithms split
your heap size into what is called a
young generation and an origin
so whenever you first create the objects
they are kept in to the young generation
of course most of them die young or they
are eligible for garbage collection very
quickly that's why you have a lot of
garbage collection run only on this
young generation and that collection is
called a minor collection if there are
objects like your class level variables
which are also called instance level
variables then they of course remain
that any or or the lifetime remains much
longer and that is why even after a lot
of minor collections when the objects
are still not eligible for garbage
collection they are promoted into this
old generation whenever there are a lot
of objects in the old generation so
let's say if the amount of space
occupied in the old generation goes
beyond the threshold for example 60% or
70% then there is a major collection
triggered because now you have to clean
up the old generation also and in this
case generally a different kind of
algorithm is run on the older generation
now the third concept that we need to
understand is the mark and copy
algorithm so within the young generation
generally the space is divided as hidden
space and to survivor spaces so all the
new objects are allocated to the hidden
space whenever time comes for a mine
collection only the live objects of this
leaden space is copied over to the cyber
survivor space and this involves both
things so it will first mark all the
objects which are live that means which
are still being used and not eligible
for garbage collection and in second
stage it will copy over all those live
objects in this survivor space either
one or two once it copies all the live
objects now this Eden space consists of
objects which are you have already
copied and the objects which are
eligible for garbage collection and that
is why this whole Eden space is wiped
out or it is just considered that it is
an empty space there is nothing of
elements there and the allocation of new
objects starts again and you can take a
look at these steps to understand why
there are two spaces survivor space one
and two the second algorithm and the
fourth concept that we need to
understand is the algorithm called
mark-sweep and compact algorithm this is
generally done on the old generation
here let's say we have a lot of
allocated objects some of them on life
some of them are eligible for garbage
collection first will mark only the live
objects right so we'll mark this object
which is live which is this object and
this object second is we will sweep and
we'll remove all the objects which are
eligible for garbage collection so we'll
remove all the spaces here at the top
and make it black generally of course
technically speaking we do not remove it
we just update a data structure behind
the scene saying that these spaces are
now empty and then the third aspect of
this is compaction so we'll move all
these live objects which are still being
used and we'll move them on to the left
side and we'll fluster them together the
advantage of this compaction is
afterwards when you when you want to
allocate new objects all you have to do
is keep a pointer here
right keep a reference that everything
on the left is being utilized everything
on the right is free and whenever you
want to allocate a new object just put
that object here and bump the pointer to
the end of that object so again
everything on the left side is being
utilized and everything on the right
side is free now that we understand all
these four concepts let's take a look at
the actual garbage collection algorithms
serial collector has the smallest
footprint of any of the collectors so
then the amount of data structures the
footprint required for this garbage
collector to run is very very minimal
this collector uses single thread for
both minor as well as miniature
collections and as we saw in the earlier
slide about compactions and bump the
pointer technique the serial collector
uses that technique to allocate any
objects and that is why allocation is
much faster this collector is generally
best for devices which are very
restrained restricted memory or if you
have your application is being run on a
shared CPU so let's imagine we have a
CPU of say quad-core CPU and we have
four applications applications running
on it if your garbage collector was not
single threaded
and it was multi-threaded then it is
possible that at some point in time your
garbage collector will start all full
threads on four cores of the CPU and
utilize that entire CPU for its own
garbage collection and that is when the
other applications running on the CPU
will suffer so if there are multiple
applications running on a single CPU and
you want to ensure that your garbage
collection does not affect other course
or other applications then you can use
serial collector the next collector to
understand is called the parallel
collector we generally only talk about
parallel old collector which uses
multiple threads for both minor GC as
well as major DC this collector does not
run concurrently with the application
okay
even though its name suggests its paddle
it's named parallel because it has
multiple threads of the garbage
collection it's
and all of those threats are
unparalleled but while the garbage
collection is running all the
application threads are stopped and that
is why if your application is deployed
on a multi-core from multiprocessor
systems then this collector will give
you the greatest throughput that is in
the shortest amount of time
it will be able to collect the highest
amount of garbage possible of course
since it stops the entire application
and it could stop it for some time it is
best only for batch applications so in
the batch application you do not care
about the users the response time
because there is no user on the front
end right it's a batch application it's
running behind the scenes so what you
want is you want the program to run as
efficiently as possible so for batch
applications the best collector to use
is a parallel collector the third
algorithm is called a CMS collector CMS
the full form of CMS is concurrent mark
and sweep and you already saw mark sweep
and compact algorithm earlier and this
is the same thing but it says it's
concurrent moppet mark and sweep that
means it runs concurrently with the
application to mark all the live objects
right so the amount of time that the
application has to stop is less so the
latency of the application is less but
of course during the actual collection
it still has STW pauses STW stop the
world forces that means it stops the
application for a very small amount of
time to do its actual garbage collection
but it's not as bad as the parallel
collector of course there are trade-offs
so it requires more footprint than
parallel collector so it has more data
structures that it needs to take care of
behind the scenes it has less throughput
than the parallel collector but the
advantage of this is it has smaller
pause times than the final collector
right and that is why it is best used
for general applications the improvement
over the CMS collector is called g1
collector g1 collected garbage post
so instead of having and specific young
generation and old generation this
collector uses the entire heap and
divides it into multiple regions and it
itself assigns whether this region is
young generation region or an old
generation region now compared to the
previous collector CMS it has more
footprint so it has even more
requirement for data structures but the
advantage of this is it this has more
predictable latency and this is the best
feature of this connector so when you
start their application you can pass on
this variable that the maximum cost time
that my application can withstand is say
10 milliseconds I cannot handle my
application cannot handle more than 10
milliseconds of cost time of course this
is not a very hard target it's a soft
target
so garbage collector the g1 collector
will try to ensure that the garbage
collection is done only for 10
milliseconds and even if there is some
garbage left then it will take care of
it in the next cycle and will allow the
application to run after 10 milliseconds
and that is why this garbage collector
the chip and collector is best for
applications which need predictable
latency so CMS was great for general
applications it has lower pastimes but
if you want predictable pastimes
predictable latency which you can set
using this variable Max target post and
then you can use the cheaper collector
there is one more collector which is
coming up which is not yet as a default
in JDK is called Shannon Dora Shannon
dower is an improvement upon g1
collector wherein it requires a little
higher footprint so it takes more data
structures behind the scenes but it has
even lower latency than g1 it's going to
come in a few versions of Java so here's
the table complete able to understand
the pros and cons so take a look in
general I would say the serial collector
is for small devices or when you want to
ensure that the GC doesn't affect other
CPUs the parallel collector is best for
batch applications the CMS application
CMS collector is best for general
applications g1 collector is best if you
want predictable latency and in Shanan
Tovah is an improvement upon g1 which
you will be able to use it as default in
few versions of Java that's it for this
video if you have any comments or
questions please let me know and see you
in the next video thank you